This meeting has really been about a digital revolution,
كان هذا اللقاء حقاً حول الثورة الرقمية،
but I'd like to argue that it's done; we won.
لكني أريد المحاججة أن ذلك قد تمّ بالفعل. لقد ربحنا.
We've had a digital revolution but we don't need to keep having it.
لقد مررنا بثورة رقمية لكننا لسنا بحاجة للمحافظة على هذا النمط.
And I'd like to look after that,
وأرغب بالنظر لما بعد ذلك،
to look what comes after the digital revolution.
لأنظر في نتائج ما بعد الثورة الرقمية.
So, let me start projecting forward.
لذا، دعوني أبدأ بإستشراف المستقبل.
These are some projects I'm involved in today at MIT,
هذه بعض المشاريع التي أشارك فيها اليوم في MIT،
looking what comes after computers.
نبحث فيما يأتي بعد الحواسيب.
This first one, Internet Zero, up here -- this is a web server
المشروع الأول، إنترنت زيرو، هاهنا -- هذا هو مخدم ويب
that has the cost and complexity of an RFID tag --
بكلفة وتعقيد تقنية RFID (تحديد الهويه باستخدام موجات الراديو)--
about a dollar -- that can go in every light bulb and doorknob,
حوالي دولار أمريكي-- التي يمكن أن توجد في كل لمبة كهربائية ومقبض باب،
and this is getting commercialized very quickly.
وهذا يتم تحويله لسلعة تجارية بسرعة كبيرة جداً.
And what's interesting about it isn't the cost;
والشئ المثير حوله ليس السعر.
it's the way it encodes the Internet.
بل الطريقة التي تُرمّز بها الإنترنت.
It uses a kind of a Morse code for the Internet
إنها تستخدم نوع من شفرة مورس للإنترنت
so you could send it optically; you can communicate acoustically
بحيث تستطيع الإرسال ضوئياً. يمكنك التواصل سمعياً
through a power line, through RF.
عبر خط الكهرباء، عبر موجات الراديو.
It takes the original principle of the Internet,
إنها تأخذ المبدأ الأصلي للإنترنت،
which is inter-networking computers,
الذي هو حواسيب موصولة ببعضها،
and now lets devices inter-network.
والآن تسمح للأجهزة بالتواصل مع بعضها البعض.
That we can take the whole idea that gave birth to the Internet
بحيث نستطيع أخذ الفكرة كاملةً التي قادت لميلاد الإنترنت
and bring it down to the physical world in this Internet Zero,
ونقوم بتحويل العالم الفيزيائي إلى هذه الإنترنت زيرو،
this internet of devices.
هذه الإنترنت من الاجهزة.
So this is the next step from there to here,
إذاً هذه هي الخطوة التالية من هناك إلى هنا،
and this is getting commercialized today.
وهذا يتم تسويقه اليوم.
A step after that is a project on fungible computers.
الخطوة التالية بعد ذلك هو مشروع الحواسيب المماثلة (قابلة للإستبدال).
Fungible goods in economics can be extended and traded.
البضائع المتداولة في الإقتصاد يمكن توسيعها والمتاجرة بها.
So, half as much grain is half as much useful,
إذاً فنصف مقدار من الحبوب مفيد جداً،
but half a baby or half a computer is less useful than
لكن نصف طفل أو نصف حاسب آلي لا فائدة منه
a whole baby or a whole computer,
مقابل طفل كامل أو حاسب آلي كامل،
and we've been trying to make computers that work that way.
لقد كنا نحاول جعل الحواسيب تعمل بتلك الطريقة.
So, what you see in the background is a prototype.
لذا، ترون نموذج على الخلفية.
This was from a thesis of a student, Bill Butow, now at Intel,
كان هذا من أطروحة الطالب، بيل ويتاو، الآن يعمل في إنتل،
who wondered why, instead of making bigger and bigger chips,
الذي تساءل لماذا، عوضاً عن صنع رقائق أكبر وأكبر،
you don't make small chips, put them in a viscous medium,
لم لا نصنع رقائق أصغر، ونضعها في وسيط لزج،
and pour out computing by the pound or by the square inch.
ونقوم بجعل الحوسبة تقدّر بالجنية أو بالبوصة المربعة.
And that's what you see here.
وهذا ما ترونه هنا.
On the left was postscript being rendered by a conventional computer;
على اليسار كان حاشية تم ترجمتها عبر جهاز حاسب تقليدي،
on the right is postscript being rendered from the first prototype
وعلى اليمين حاشية تم ترجمتها عبر النموذج الأول
we made, but there's no frame buffer, IO processor,
الذي صنعناه، لكن بدون إطار عازل، أو معالج إدخال وإخراج،
any of that stuff -- it's just this material.
أو أي من هذه الأشياء-- بل هذه المادة فقط.
Unlike this screen where the dots are placed carefully,
خلافاً لهذه الشاشة حيث تم وضع النقاط بصورة حذرة،
this is a raw material.
هاهي المادة الخام.
If you add twice as much of it, you have twice as much display.
إذا وضعت مقدار الضعف منها، تحصل على مقدار الضعف من العرض.
If you shoot a gun through the middle, nothing happens.
إذا قمت بإطلاق نار من بندقية في المنتصف، لن يحدث شئ.
If you need more resource, you just apply more computer.
إذا أردت موارد أكثر، فقط تقوم بطلب حواسيب أكثر.
So, that's the step after this -- of computing as a raw material.
لذا، تلك خطوة بعد هذا -- لحوسبة المواد الخام.
That's still conventional bits, the step after that is --
ما يزال هذا بوحدة "بت" تقليدية، والخطوة التالية بعد هذا --
this is an earlier prototype in the lab;
هذا نموذج أولي في المختبر،
this is high-speed video slowed down.
هذا فيديو سريع التصوير تم إبطاؤه.
Now, integrating chemistry in computation, where the bits are bubbles.
الآن، دمج الكيمياء في الحوسبة، حيث القطع والفقاقيع.
This is showing making bits, this is showing --
يعرض هذا صنع "البتتات"، وهذا يعرض...
once again, slowed down so you can see it,
مرة أخرى، تم إبطاؤها بحيث تستطيعون رؤيتها،
bits interacting to do logic and multiplexing and de-multiplexing.
تتفاعل البتتات لتقوم بعمليات منطقية وضرب وقسمة.
So, now we can compute that the output arranges material
الآن يمكننا حساب أن الناتج يرتّب المادة
as well as information. And, ultimately, these are some slides
وكذلك المعلومات. وفي نهاية المطاف، هذه بعض الشرائح
from an early project I did, computing where the bits are stored
من بدايات المشروع الذي أنجزته، الحوسبة حيث يتم تخزين البتات
quantum-mechanically in the nuclei of atoms, so
بميكانيكيا الكم في أنوية الذرات، بحيث
programs rearrange the nuclear structure of molecules.
تعيد البرمجة ترتيب بنية الجزيئات النووية.
All of these are in the lab pushing further and further and further,
كل هذه في المختبر تتقدم أكثر وأكثر،
not as metaphor but literally integrating bits and atoms,
ليس من قبيل المجاز بل حرفياً تندمج البتات والجزيئات،
and they lead to the following recognition.
ويقود هذا للتعرف الذي يليه.
We all know we've had a digital revolution, but what is that?
جميعنا قد شهد الثورة الرقمية، لكن ما هو ذلك؟
Well, Shannon took us, in the '40s, from here to here:
حسناً، نقلنا شاننون، في أربعينات القرن الماضي، من هنا إلى هنا:
from a telephone being a speaker wire that degraded with distance
من كون الهاتف عبارة عن سماعة موصولة تقل كفائتها مع المسافة
to the Internet. And he proved the first threshold theorem, that shows
للإنترنت. وقد أثبت أول نظريات الكم (threshold theorem)
if you add information and remove it to a signal,
وهي إن قمت بإضافة معلومات ثم حذفتها من الإشارة،
you can compute perfectly with an imperfect device.
يمكنك الحوسبة بكفاءة بدون الحوجة لجهاز قوي(مكتمل).
And that's when we got the Internet.
وحينئذ حصلنا على الإنترنت.
Von Neumann, in the '50s, did the same thing for computing;
فعل فون نيومان في الخمسينات نفس الشئ مع الحوسبة.
he showed you can have an unreliable computer but restore its state
لقد أثبت أنك يمكن أن تحصل على حاسب غير مستقر لكنه يستعيد حالته
to make it perfect. This was the last great analog computer at MIT:
لتحسينها. كان هذا آخر حاسب تناظري ضخم في معهد MIT:
a differential analyzer, and the more you ran it,
محلل تفاضلي، وكلما شغلته أكثر،
the worse the answer got.
كلما أصبحت الإجابة بعيدةً من الصواب
After Von Neumann, we have the Pentium, where the billionth transistor
وبعد فون نيومان، كان لدينا نتيوم، حيث أصبحت مليارات الترانزيستورات
is as reliable as the first one.
مستقرة مثل أول واحد منها.
But all our fabrication is down in this lower left corner.
وكل تخليقاتنا في هذا الجزء السفلي على اليسار.
A state-of-the-art airplane factory rotating metal wax at fixed metal,
مصنع طائرات حديث الطراز يدور شمع معدني في معدن مثبّت،
or you maybe melt some plastic. A 10-billion-dollar chip fab
أو ربما تذويب بعض البلاستيك. إن تخليق شريحة سعرها 10 دولارات
uses a process a village artisan would recognize --
يستخدم ما يناظر حرفيّ قرية كاملة --
you spread stuff around and bake it.
فأنت تقوم بنشر الأدوات وتخبزها.
All the intelligence is external to the system;
كل الذكاء خارجي بالنسبة للنظام.
the materials don't have information.
ليس للمواد أي معلومات.
Yesterday you heard about molecular biology,
لقد سمعتم بالأمس شيئاً عن الأحياء الجزيئية،
which fundamentally computes to build.
التي تقوم بحسابات البناء.
It's an information processing system.
وهي نظام معالجة للمعلومات.
We've had digital revolutions in communication and computation,
لقد شهدنا ثورة رقمية في الإتصالات والحوسبة،
but precisely the same idea, precisely the same math
لكن بكل دقة نفس الفكرة ونفس الحسابات
Shannon and Von Neuman did, hasn't yet come out
التي قام بها شانون وفون نيومان، لم تخرج
to the physical world. So, inspired by that,
للعالم الفيزيائي. لذا، فقد أُلهم
colleagues in this program -- the Center for Bits and Atoms
زملاء في هذا البرنامج -- مركز البتات والجزيئات
at MIT -- which is a group of people, like me,
في أم آي تي -- التي هي مجموعة من الناس مثلي،
who never understood the boundary between physical science
الذين لم يعرفوا حدود بين العلوم الفيزيائية
and computer science. I would even go further and say
وعلوم الحاسوب. وقد استطرد أكثر لأقول
computer science is one of the worst things that ever happened
أن علوم الحاسوب هي أحد اسوأ الأشياء التي قد تحدث
to either computers or to science --
للحواسيب أو للعلوم --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
-- because the canon -- computer science --
--لأن شرعة علوم الحاسوب --
many of them are great but the canon of computer science
الكثير منها عظيم لكن شرعة علوم الحاسوب
prematurely froze a model of computation
قامت بتجميد نموذج الحوسبة قبل أوانه
based on technology that was available in 1950,
بناء على تكنلوجيات كانت متاحة عام 1950
and nature's a much more powerful computer than that.
والطبيعة تمثّل حاسوباً أقوى بكثير من ذلك.
So, you'll hear, tomorrow, from Saul Griffith. He was one of the
ستستمعون غداً لساول غيريفس. لقد كان أحد أول
first students to emerge from this program.
الطلاب يظهر عبر هذا البرنامج.
We started to figure out how you can compute to fabricate.
لقد بدأنا معرفة كيف يمكن أن نحسب للتخليق.
This was just a proof of principle he did of tiles
لقد كان هذا مجرد إثبات لمبدأ أثبته للبلاط
that interact magnetically, where you write a code,
الذي يتفاعل مغناطيسيا، حيث قام بكتابة برنامج،
much like protein folding, that specifies their structure.
أشبه بطيّ البروتين، الذي يحدد هيكلها.
So, there's no feedback to a tool metrology;
وعليه ليس هناك إستيعاب من أداة قياس،
the material itself codes for its structure in just the same ways
فالمواد نفسها تقوم بالبرنامج المناسب لهيكلها بنفس الطرق
that protein are fabricated. So, you can, for example, do that.
التي يتخلق بها البروتين. وعليه يمكنك على سبيل المثال فعل ذلك.
You can do other things. That's in 2D. It works in 3D.
يمكنك فعل أشياء أخرى. ثنائية الأبعاد. وتعمل أيضاً في الأبعاد الثلاثية.
The video on the upper right -- I won't show for time --
الفيديو في الجزء الأعلى على اليمين -- لن أعرضه لقصر الزمن --
shows self-replication, templating so something can make something
يظهر إستنساخ ذاتي، قولبة، شئ يمكن أن يصنع شيئاً
that can make something, and we're doing that now over, maybe,
يمكن أن يصنع شئ آخر، ونحن ربما نفعل ذلك الآن،
nine orders of magnitude. Those ideas have been used to show
تسعة أضعاف المقدار. تلك الأفكار أُستخدمت لإظهار
the best fidelity and direct rate DNA to make an organism,
أن أفضل دقة ومعدل مباشر للحمض النووي لصنع كائن،
in functionalizing nanoclusters with peptide tails
في تشغيل عناقيد نانو مع أحماض بيبتايد
that code for their assembly -- so, much like the magnets,
التي تقوم ببرمجة تجمعها. أشبه بالمغناطيس،
but now on nanometer scales.
لكنها الآن على قياس نانو متر.
Laser micro-machining: essentially 3D printers that digitally fabricate
ماكينات الليزر الماكرو: هي طابعات ثلاثية الأبعاد تقوم بتخليق رقمي
functional systems, all the way up to building buildings,
أنظمة تشغيلية، حتى إنشاء المنشآت،
not by having blueprints,
ليس عبر المخططات،
but having the parts code for the structure of the building.
بل بالحصول على جزء من الشفرة لهيكل البناء.
So, these are early examples in the lab of emerging technologies
وهناك أمثلة مبكرة في المختبر لتكنلوجيات حديثة
to digitize fabrication. Computers that don't control tools
لرقمنة التخليق. لا تتحكم الحواسيب في الأدوات
but computers that are tools, where the output of a program
بل الحاسبات نفسها هي الأدوات، حيث يقوم يكون مخرجات البرنامج
rearranges atoms as well as bits.
هي إعادة تنظيم الجزيئات وكذلك البتات.
Now, to do that -- with your tax dollars, thank you --
الآن، لفعل ذلك -- وبفضل أموال ضرائبكم ، شكراً لكم --
I bought all these machines. We made a modest proposal
أشتريت هذه الآلات. وطورنا مقترح مقنع
to the NSF. We wanted to be able to make anything on any length scale,
لجمعية العلوم الوطنية. أردنا أن نقدر على صنع أي شئ في أي طول
all in one place, because you can't segregate digital fabrication
جميعها في مكان واحد، لأننا لا نستطيع فصل التخليق الرقمي
by a discipline or a length scale.
بالتخصص أو بحجم الطول.
So we put together focused nano beam writers
لذا فقد وضعنا سويةً كاتبات أشعة نانو
and supersonic water jet cutters and excimer micro-machining systems.
وقاطعات مياة سوبر سونيك و أنظمة محمس ديمر بماكينات بحجم المايكرو.
But I had a problem. Once I had all these machines,
لكن واجهتني مشكلة. بمجرد حصولي على هذه الماكينات
I was spending too much time teaching students to use them.
كنت أقضي وقتاً طويلاً في تعليم الطلاب كيفية استخدامها
So I started teaching a class, modestly called,
لذا بدأت تدريس منهج ، يسمى
"How To Make Almost Anything." And that wasn't meant to be provocative;
" كيف يمكنك صنع أي شئ تقريباً." ولم يعني هذا أن أكون إستفزازياً،
it was just for a few research students.
لقد كان لبعض الباحثين.
But the first day of class looked like this.
وبدى أول يوم في الدرس هكذا
You know, hundreds of people came in begging,
جاء مئات الطلاب يطلبون الفرصة
all my life I've been waiting for this class; I'll do anything to do it.
ويقولون كنا طوال حياتنا نتوق لهذا الفصل الدراسي، وسأفعل أي شئ لأحضره.
Then they'd ask, can you teach it at MIT? It seems too useful?
ثم يسألون، هل يمكنك تدريسه في أم آي تي؟ يبدو مفيداً جداً!
And then the next --
ثم بعد ذلك --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
-- surprising thing was they weren't there to do research.
-- الشئ المفاجئ أنهم لم يكونوا هناك من أجل البحث
They were there because they wanted to make stuff.
لقد كانوا هناك ليتمكنوا من صنع الأشياء
They had no conventional technical background.
لم يكن لديهم أي خلفية تقنية معتادة
At the end of a semester they integrated their skills.
وبنهاية الفصل الدراسي قاموا بتجميع مهاراتهم
I'll show an old video. Kelly was a sculptor, and this is what she did
سأريكم الفيديو القديم. كانت كيلي هي النحات، وهذا ما فعلته
with her semester project.
أثناء مشروع الفصل الدراسي.
(Video): Kelly: Hi, I'm Kelly and this is my scream buddy.
(فيديو): كيلي: مرحباً، أنا كيلي وهذا هو صديقي في الصراخ.
Do you ever find yourself in a situation
هل حدث أن وجدت نفسك في وضعية
where you really have to scream, but you can't because you're at work,
أنك تريد الصراخ بالفعل، لكن لا يمكنك ذلك بسبب العمل،
or you're in a classroom, or you're watching your children,
أو أنك في فصل دراسي، أو تقوم برعاية أطفالك،
or you're in any number of situations where it's just not permitted?
أو في أي وضعية حيث ليس مسموحاً لك بذلك؟
Well, scream buddy is a portable space for screaming.
حسناً، صديقي للصراخ هو مكان محمول للصراخ.
When a user screams into scream buddy, their scream is silenced.
عندما يصرخ المستخدم داخل صديقي للصراخ، فان صرختهم يتم إخراسها
It is also recorded for later release where, when and how
ويتم تسجيلها أيضاً لإطلاقها لاحقاً، متى وكيف
the user chooses.
ما أراد المستخدم.
(Scream)
(صراخ)
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)
So, Einstein would like this.
لابد أن إينشتاين سيُعجب بهذا
This student made a web browser for parrots --
هذا الطالب صنع مستكشف إنترنت للببغاوات
lets parrots surf the Net and talk to other parrots.
يمكّن الببغاوات من إستكشاف الإنترنت والتحدث مع الببغاوات الأخرى
This student's made an alarm clock you wrestle
هذا الطالب صنع ساعة بمنبه تصارعها
to prove you're awake; this is one that defends --
لتثبت أنك صاحي، هذه هي التي تقاوم --
a dress that defends your personal space.
ملبس يقاوم فضاءك الشخصي
This isn't technology for communication;
هذا ليست تقنية للاتصالات
it's technology to prevent it.
إنها تقنية لمنع ذلك
This is a device that lets you see your music.
هذا جهاز يجعلها ترى الموسيقى
This is a student who made a machine that makes machines,
هذا الطالب صنع آلة تقوم بصنع الآلات
and he made it by making Lego bricks that do the computing.
وقد صنعها عبر طوب ليغو يقوم بالحوسبة
Just year after year -- and I finally realized
بعد عام فقط -- وقد أدركت
the students were showing the killer app of personal fabrication
أن الطلاب كانوا يعرضون الأدلة للتخليق
is products for a market of one person.
وهي نتاج لسوق يناسب شخص واحد
You don't need this for what you can get in Wal-Mart;
فانت لست بحاجة لهذا مقابل ما تحصل عليه في متجر وول مارت
you need this for what makes you unique.
أنت بحاجة لهذا لما يجعلك متفردا
Ken Olsen famously said, nobody needs a computer in the home.
مقولة كين أولسن الشهيرة، يحتاج أي شخص لحاسوب في البيت
But you don't use it for inventory and payroll;
لكنك لا تستخدمه لقوائم الجرد والكشوفات
DEC is now twice bankrupt. You don't need personal fabrication
ديك هي الآن تويز التي أفلست. فانت لست بحاجة للتخليق الشخصي
in the home to buy what you can buy because you can buy it.
في البيت لشراء ما يمكنه شراؤه لأنه يمكنك شراؤه
You need it for what makes you unique, just like personalization.
أنت بحاجة له ليجعلك متفردا، تماماً مثل التصنيع للشخص
So, with that, in turn, 20 million dollars today does this;
وعليه في المقابل، فما تطلب 20 مليون دولار اليوم،
20 years from now we'll make Star Trek replicators that make anything.
بعد 20 سنة من الآن يمكن أن يصنع ناسخ ستار تريك يمكن أن يصنع أي شئ
The students hijacked all the machines I bought to do personal fabrication.
وقد إختطف الطلاب كل الآلات التي أشتريتها لإنشاء تخليقات شخصية
Today, when you spend that much of your money,
اليوم، عندما تنفق ذلك الحجم من أموالك
there's a government requirement to do outreach, which often means
فهناك متطلبات حكومية لتقوم بفصول توعية، الذي يعني عادةً
classes at a local school, a website -- stuff that's just not that exciting.
فصول في المدارس المحلية، موقع إنترنت، أشياء ليست مثيرة
So, I made a deal with my NSF program managers that
لذا فقد عقدت صفقة مع مديري برنامج المؤسسة الوطنية للعلوم
instead of talking about it, I'd give people the tools.
بدلاً من الحديث عنه، سأعطي الناس الأدوات
This wasn't meant to be provocative or important,
لم يكن المقصود هو الإستفزاز أو الأهمية
but we put together these Fab Labs. It's about 20,000 dollars in equipment
لكننا نضع هذه المختبرات الفاب. وهي تساوي ما قيمته 20 ألف دولار من الادوات
that approximate both what the 20 million dollars does and where it's going.
التي تساوي تقريباً ما كانت تفعله 20 مليون دولار
A laser cutter to do press-fit assembly with 3D from 2D,
قاطع ليزر للقيام بعملية تجميع وضغط يتناسب مع ثنائية وثلاثية الأبعاد
a sign cutter to plot in copper to do electromagnetics,
وقاطع علامة لحبك النحاس في الكهرمغنطيسية
a micron scale,
بحجم ميكرون
numerically-controlled milling machine for precise structures,
وآلة طحن دقيقة يتحكم فيها عبر الأعداد لهيكل دقيق،
programming tools for less than a dollar,
أدوات برمجة مقابل أقل من دولار
100-nanosecond microcontrollers. It lets you work from microns
متحكمات بدقة 100 نانو ثانية. وتمكّنك من العمل من المايكرونات
and microseconds on up, and they exploded around the world.
والمايكروثانية ولأعلى، وقد أنتشرت عبر العالم.
This wasn't scheduled, but they went from inner-city Boston
لم يكن هذا في الحسبان، لكنها أنتشرت من داخل من مدينة بوسطن
to Pobal in India, to Secondi-Takoradi on Ghana's coast
إلى بوبال في الهند، إلى سكوندي- تاكورادي في ساحل غانا
to Soshanguve in a township in South Africa,
إلى سوشانغيوزي في مدينة في جنوب أفريقيا
to the far north of Norway, uncovering, or helping uncover,
حتى الشمال البعيد في النرويج، تقوم بالكشف عن، أو تساعد في إسترعاء
for all the attention to the digital divide,
الإنتباه للفارق الرقمي
we would find unused computers in all these places.
وقد نجد حواسيب غير مستخدمة في كل هذه الأماكن
A farmer in a rural village -- a kid needs to measure and modify
مزارع في قرية ريفية -- وطفل بحاجة لقياس وتعديل
the world, not just get information about it on a screen.
العالم، ليس فقط الحصول على المعلومات عبر الشاشة
That there's really a fabrication and an instrumentation divide
حيث أن هناك حقاً فوارق في المعدات والتخليق
bigger than the digital divide.
أكبر بكثير من الفارق الرقمي
And the way you close it is not IT for the masses but IT development for the masses.
والطريقة التي تكشف بها ذلك ليس عبر تقنية المعلومات لكن بتطويرها للجماهير
So, in place after place
لذا ففي مكان وآخر يليه
we saw this same progression: that we'd open one of these Fab Labs,
شهدنا نفس التقدم: أن علينا فتح أحد مختبرات الفاب هذه،
where we didn't -- this is too crazy to think of.
حيث لم نكن فعلنا ذلك -- وهذا جنوني حقاً لتفكر به.
We didn't think this up, that we would get pulled to these places;
لم نكن قد فكرنا لهذه الدرجة، بأننا سننجذب لهذه المناطق،
we'd open it. The first step was just empowerment.
وأننا سنفتحها. والخطوة الأولى كانت مجرد تمكين
You can see it in their face, just this joy of, I can do it.
يمكنك رؤية وجوههم، وهذه المتعة، إن أستطعت فعلها.
This is a girl in inner-city Boston who had just done a high-tech
هذه الفتاة في مدينة بوسطن التي قد باعت للتو مركبة عالية التقنية
on-demand craft sale in the inner city community center.
بيع للمنتوجات اليدوية عند الطلب في مركز مجتمع المدينة
It goes on from there to serious hands-on technical education
إن الأمر يبدأ من مسودات تعليم تقني جادة
informally, out of schools. In Ghana we had set up one of these labs.
غير رسمية، خارج المدرسة. في غانا قمنا باعداد أحدى هذه المختبرات
We designed a network sensor, and kids would show up
لقد صممنا شبكة مجسات، ويأتي الأطفال
and refuse to leave the lab.
ويرفضون مغادرة المختبر
There was a girl who insisted we stay late at night --
وهذه الفتاة أصرت على البقاء حتى أواخر الليل--
(Video): Kids: I love the Fab Lab.
(فيديو): أطفال: أحب مختبرات فاب
-- her first night in the lab because she was going to make the sensor.
-- أولى لياليها في المختبر لأنها كانت بصدد صنع مجس
So she insisted on fabbing the board, learning how to stuff it,
لذا فقد أصرت على تخليق اللوحة، وتعلم كيفية توصيلها
learning how to program it. She didn't really know
وتعلم كيفية برمجتها.
what she was doing or why she was doing it, but she knew
مالذي تفعله أو لماذا تفعله، لكنها عرفت
she just had to do it. There was something electric about it.
أنها تفعل هذا الشئ. وأن هناك شيئاً إلكترونياً حول الأمر
This is late at, you know, 11 o'clock at night
كان هذا في وقت متأخر 11 مساء
and I think I was the only person surprised when what she built
وأعتقد أنني كنت الوحيد الذي دُهش عندما قامت ببناء
worked the first time.
والعمل لأول مرة
And I've shown this to engineers at big companies, and they say
كنت أعرض هذا على مهندسين في شركات كبرى، ويقولون
they can't do this. Any one thing she's doing, they can do better,
أنهم لا يستطيعون فعل ذلك. أي شئ تقوم بفعله، يمكنهم فعله بصورة أفضل
but it's distributed over many people and many sites
لكنها منتشرة عبر العديد من الناس والأماكن
and they can't do in an afternoon
ولا يمكنهم في الظهيرة فعل
what this little girl in rural Ghana is doing.
ما تفعله الفتاة في منطقة ريفية في غانا.
(Video): Girl: My name is Valentina Kofi; I am eight years old.
(فيديو) : فتاة: أسمي فالينتينا كوفي، وأبلغ الثامنة من العمر
I made a stacking board.
لقد صنعت لوحة تراص
And, again, that was just for the joy of it.
ومجدداً، كان هذا مجرد متعتها.
Then these labs started doing serious problem solving --
ثم بدأت هذه المختبرات في حلحلة مشاكل عويصة --
instrumentation for agriculture in India,
أجهزة زراعية في الهند،
steam turbines for energy conversion in Ghana,
مولدات بخار لحفظ الطاقة في غانا،
high-gain antennas in thin client computers.
هوائيات عالية الإستقطاب في حاسوب مستخدم
And then, in turn, businesses started to grow,
ثم بدأت الأعمال في التنامي
like making these antennas.
مثل صنع هذه الهوائيات
And finally, the lab started doing invention.
وأخيراً، بدأ المختبر في فعل الإبتكارات
We're learning more from them than we're giving them.
نحن نتعلم منهم أكثر مما نعطيهم
I was showing my kids in a Fab Lab how to use it.
كنت أعرض لأطفالي في مختبر الفاب كيفية إستخدامه
They invented a way to do a construction kit out of a cardboard box --
ثم أبتكروا طريقة لفعل حزمة البناء باستخدام مربع من الورق المقوى--
which, as you see up there, that's becoming a business --
الشئ الذي كما ترون هناك، يتحول لعمل تجاري --
but their design was better than Saul's design at MIT,
لكن تصميمهم كان أفضل من تصميم ساول في معهد ماساتشوستس للتكنولوجيا
so there's now three students at MIT doing their theses on
إذاً، هناك ثلاث طلاب في معهد ماساتشوستس للتكنولوجيا يعدون رسالتهم
scaling the work of eight-year-old children
في تكبير حجم عمل الأطفال 8 سنوات
because they had better designs.
لأن لديهم تصميمات أفضل
Real invention is happening in these labs.
إبتكارات حقيقية تحدث في هذه المختبرات
And I still kept -- so, in the last year I've been spending time with
وفي العام الماضي كنت أقضي الوقت مع
heads of state and generals and tribal chiefs who all want this,
رؤساء الدول وقادة الجيش وزعماء القبائل الذين يريدون هذا،
and I keep saying, but this isn't the real thing.
وظللت أقول، لكن هذا ليس شيئاً كاملاً
Wait, like, 20 years and then we'll be done.
مهلاً، بعد 20 عاماً سيكتمل
And I finally got what's been going on. This is Kernigan and Ritchie
وأخيراً حصلت على المستجدات. هذه كرنيجان وريتشي
inventing UNIX on a PDP.
يبتكرون نظام يونكس على معالج بيانات مبرمجة PDP
PDPs came between mainframes and minicomputers.
جاء المعالج PDP ما بين حقبة الحواسيب الضخمة والصغيرة
They were tens of thousands of dollars, hard to use,
كان سعرها عشرات الآلاف من الدولارات، وصعبة الإستخدام
but they brought computing down to work groups,
لكنها أحدثت فرقاً في إيصال الحوسبة لمجموعات العمل
and everything we do today happened there.
وكل ما نفعله اليوم يحدث هناك
These Fab Labs are the cost and complexity of a PDP.
مختبرات الفاب هذه بكلفة وتعقيد ال PDP
The projection of digital fabrication
إن توقعات التخليق الرقمي
isn't a projection for the future; we are now in the PDP era.
ليست توقعات للمستقبل. نحن الآن في حقبة ال PDP
We talked in hushed tones about the great discoveries then.
لقد تحدثنا بأصوات خافتة عن الإكتشافات العظيمة حينئذ
It was very chaotic, it wasn't, sort of, clear what was going on.
لقد كانت فوضوية للغاية وواضح للعيان مالذي يجري
In the same sense we are now, today, in the minicomputer era
ونحن اليوم بنفس الروح في حقبة الحواسيب الصغيرة
of digital fabrication.
للتخليق الرقمي
The only problem with that is it breaks everybody's boundaries.
المشكلة الوحيدة لذلك هي أنها تكسر حواجز الجميع
In DC, I go to every agency that wants to talk, you know;
في واشنطن، أزور أي وكالة ترغب في الحديث
in the Bay Area, I go to every organization you can think of --
في منطقة الخليج، أذهب لأي منظمة يمكنكم التفكير بها
they all want to talk about it, but it breaks
جميعهم يرغب بالحديث عن ذلك، لكنها
their organizational boundaries. In fact, it's illegal for them,
تكسر حواجز مؤسساتهم. في الواقع، ليس قانونياً لهم
in many cases, to equip ordinary people to create
في كثير من الأحوال، تزويد العامة بالمعدات للإنتاج
rather than consume technology.
عوضاً عن إستهلاك التكنلوجيا
And that problem is so severe that the ultimate invention
وهذه المشكلة كبيرة بحيث أن الإبتكار النهائي
coming from this community surprised me:
الذي يأتي من هذا المجتمع يدهشني
it's the social engineering. That the lab in far north of Norway --
إنها هندسة إجتماعية. حيث أن المختبر في أقصى شمال النرويج --
this is so far north its satellite dishes look at the ground
ذلك الشمال الأقصى حيث تقبع أطباق الأقمار الصناعية على الأرض
rather than the sky because that's where the satellites are --
عوضاً عن السماء لأن الفضاء هناك --
the lab outgrew the little barn that it was in.
نمى المختبر أكثر بكثير من الحظيرة الصغيرة التي كان فيها
It was there because they wanted to find animals in the mountains
كان هناك لأنهم أرادوا العثور على حيوانات في الجبال
but it outgrew it, so they built this extraordinary village for the lab.
لكنه نمى كثيراً، حتى بنوا قرية أكبر من أجل المختبر
This isn't a university; it's not a company. It's essentially
هذه ليست جامعة، وليست شركة أيضاً، إنها
a village for invention; it's a village for the outliers in society,
قرية للإبتكارات، إنها قرية للمهمشين في المجتمع
and those have been growing up around these Fab Labs
وهؤلاء ظلوا يترعرعون حول مختبرات الفاب هذه
all around the world.
في كل أرجاء العالم
So this program has split into an NGO foundation,
لذا توجّب أن ينقسم هذا البرنامج إلى مؤسسة غير ربحية
a Fab Foundation to support the scaling, a micro VC fund.
مؤسسة فاب لدعم توسعة المشروع، و دعومات رأسمال مجازف
The person who runs it nicely describes it as
الشخص الذي يدير المؤسسة يصفها بكل لطف
"machines that make machines need businesses that make businesses:"
بأنها معدات تصنع معدات، تحتاج لأعمال تصنع أعمال:
it's a cross between micro-finance and VC to do fan-out,
إنها حلقة ما بين التمويل الأصغر ورأس المال المجازف
and then the research partnerships back at MIT for what's
ثم الشراكة البحثية مع معهد ماساتشوستس للتكنولوجيا
making it possible.
ليجعل الأمر ممكنا
So I'd like to leave you with two thoughts.
لذا أرغب في أترككم مع هاتين الخاطرتين
There's been a sea change in aid, from top-down mega-projects
هناك تغيير مياه في المساعدات، من نموذج أعلى لأسفل في مشروعات ضخمة
to bottom-up, grassroots, micro-finance investing in the roots,
لنموذج من أسفل لأعلى، من الجذور، تمويل أصغر يستثمر في الجذور
so that everybody's got that that's what works.
بحيث يحصل الجميع على ما ينفعهم وينجح
But we still look at technology as top-down mega-projects.
لكننا ما نزال ننظر للتكنلوجيا كمشاريع ضخمة من أعلى لأسفل
Computing, communication, energy for the rest of the planet
الحوسبة، الإتصالات، الطاقة لبقية سكان الكوكب
are these top-down mega-projects.
هذه مشاريع ضخمة من أعلى لأسفل
If this room full of heroes is just clever enough,
إذا كانت هذه القاعة مليئة بالأبطال الأذكياء بما يكفي،
you can solve the problems.
يمكنك حل كل المشاكل
The message coming from the Fab Labs is that
إن الرسالة القادمة من مختبرات فاب هي
the other five billion people on the planet
أن بقية الخمس مليارات نسمة في كوكب الأرض
aren't just technical sinks; they're sources.
ليسوا مجرد مستهلكي تقنية. إنهم مصادر للتقنية
The real opportunity is to harness the inventive power of the world
وأن الفرصة الحقيقية هي أن نجني القوى المبتكرة للعالم
to locally design and produce solutions to local problems.
لتصميم وإنتاج حلول محلية للمشاكل المحلية
I thought that's the projection 20 years hence into the future,
أعتقدت أن هذا هو توقع ل 20 عاماً في المستقبل
but it's where we are today.
لكن هذا ما نحن عليه اليوم
It breaks every organizational boundary we can think of.
إنها تكسر كل أسوار المؤسسات التي يمكن التفكير بها
The hardest thing at this point is the social engineering
الشئ الأصعب في هذه المرحلة هو الهندسة الإجتماعية
and the organizational engineering, but it's here today.
والهندسة المؤسساتية، لكن الأمر هنا اليوم.
And, finally, any talk like this on the future of computing
وأخيراً، إن أي حديث مثل هذا حول مستقبل الحوسبة
is required to show Moore's law, but my favorite version --
يظل مطلوباً لإثبات/نفي قانون موراي، لكن نسختي المفضلة --
this is Gordon Moore's original one from his original paper --
هذا هو قانون غوردون موراي الأصلي من الورقة الأصلية --
and what's happened is, year after year after year,
وما حدث هو، سنة بعد سنة،
we've scaled and we've scaled and we've scaled
لقد توسعنا وتوسعنا وتوسعنا
and we've scaled, and we've scaled and we've scaled,
وتوسعنا، وتوسعنا أكثر وأكثر،
and there's this looming bug of what's going to happen
ويوجد خطأ يلوح في الأفق حول ما سيحدث
at the end of Moore's law; this ultimate bug is coming.
عند نهاية قانون موراي. إن الخطأ النهائي قادم
But we're coming to appreciate, is the transition from 2D to 3D,
لكننا سنقدّر هذا الإنتقال من الثنائي الأبعدا، للثلاثي الأبعاد
from programming bits to programming atoms,
من برمجة البتات والجزيئات،
turns the ends of Moore's law scaling from the ultimate bug
وضح أن قانون موراي يتوسع من الخطأ النهائي
to the ultimate feature.
إلى الميزة النهائية
So, we're just at the edge of this digital revolution in fabrication,
إذاً ، فنحن على حافة ثورة التخليق الرقمية هذه،
where the output of computation programs the physical world.
حيث سيكون مخرجات البرامج الحاسوبية هي العالم الفيزيائي.
So, together, these two projects answer questions
لذا، فهذين المشروعين مجتمعين يجيبان على الأسئلة
I hadn't asked carefully. The class at MIT shows the killer app
لم اسأل بحرص. لقد برهن الفصل في معهد MIT أن التطبيق
for personal fabrication in the developed world
للتخليق الشخصي في العالم المتقدم
is technology for a market of one: personal expression in technology
هي التكنلوجيا لسوق من شخص واحد: التعبير الشخصي في التكنلوجيا
that touches a passion unlike anything I've seen in technology
وذلك يلامس الشغف خلافاً لأي شئ رأيناه في التكنلوجيا
for a very long time.
لزمن طويل.
And the killer app for the rest of the planet is the instrumentation
والتطبيق المبرهن لبقية الكوكب هو الأجهزة
and the fabrication divide: people locally developing solutions
والفارق التخليقي- عبر المختبرات- : يطوّر الناس حلولاً محلية
to local problems. Thank you.
لمشاكل محلية. شكراً لكم.